[
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>It is impossible to satisfy all human wants because:<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong><br \/><br \/><br \/><\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "of income inequality",
      "available resources are limited",
      "human wants are unlimited",
      "money income is limited"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>Mr. Tola needs a book and a calculator that cost N70 each. If he buys the book instead of the calculator, the opportunity cost of his choice is?<\/strong><br><br><br><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "N70",
      "N140",
      "Calculator",
      "Book"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>The meaning of scale of preference is:<\/strong><br \/><strong>&nbsp;<\/strong><br \/><strong>&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "a list of consumers wants, arranged in order of importance",
      "the preparation of a list of goods and services that satisfy wants",
      "the consumer budget",
      "the consumer preference for cheap goods"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>The knowledge of Economics enables an individual to:<\/strong><br \/><br \/><br \/><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "be careful in the spending of his income",
      "derive maximum satisfaction from the use of his resources",
      "be investment conscious",
      "avoid the purchase of harmful goods"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>If you do not have to make any sacrifice in order to get a particular thing then its real cost is:<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "its price",
      "zero",
      "infinite",
      "one"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>Which of the following defines Economics most comprehensively?<\/strong><br \/><br \/><br \/><br \/><br \/><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "Organization of industries and services to produce utility",
      "Study of human behaviour in the allocation of scarce resources",
      "Buying and selling of goods and services",
      "Study of economic agents in allocation of goods and services"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>MUA = PA where A = good, A:P = price of good A; MU = Marginal Utility<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>The above equation represents:<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "total utility equation",
      "Marginal utility equation",
      "equilibrium equation",
      "Utility maximization equation"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 4,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>For a free commodity, a rational consumer will continuously increase his consumption until:<\/strong><br \/><br \/><br \/><br \/><strong>&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "his marginal utility becomes zero",
      "he attains the highest marginal utility level",
      "his marginal utility equal the price he would have paid",
      "he decides to stop"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>A rational consumer will adjust his spending pattern so that:<\/strong><br \/><br \/><br \/><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "the marginal utility he gets from the last naira spent on each item is the same&nbsp;",
      "the total amount of money he spends on each item is the same",
      "the total utility he gets from each item is the same",
      "the marginal utility he gets from the last unit of each item is the same"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>The sum of all the marginal utilities a consumer derives from the consumption of extra units of a&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>commodity is known as:<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "average utility",
      "time utility",
      "total utility",
      "marginal utility"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>The demand for a commodity not directly for immediate consumption but for the production of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>another commodity is:<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "joint demand",
      "composite demand",
      "derived demand",
      "competitive demand"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>Demand in Economics is synonymous with:<\/strong><br \/><br \/><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "needs of a rational consumer",
      "all goods demanded in the market at a time",
      "wants of the consumer at a time",
      "wants backed with ability to pay"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 4,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>The responsiveness of demand to a change in income is termed:<\/strong><br \/><br \/><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "income elasticity of demand",
      "cross elasticity of demand",
      "price elasticity of demand",
      "money income index"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>In Ekiti State, the demand curve for rice in every household is downward sloping because:<\/strong><br \/><br \/><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "the higher the price of rice, the lower the quantity of rice to be demanded",
      "rice is produced in the state",
      "every household has access to the market",
      "there is excess supply"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>An increase in the demand for pen raises the demand for ink. This type of demand is called:<\/strong><br \/><strong>&nbsp;<\/strong><br \/><strong>&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "competitive demand",
      "composite demand",
      "complementary demand",
      "derived demand"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>A good example of a free good is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "education",
      "security",
      "air",
      "mineral resources"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>The decision on what to produce is a problem in<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "developing economic systems",
      "all economic systems",
      "a centrally planned economic system only",
      "a free-enterprise economic system only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>Which of the following would not be included in the fundamental principle of a free enterprise economy?<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "the right to make private profit",
      "government control factor of production",
      "private ownership of factors of production",
      "government encourages competitive capitalism within the legal framework of the country"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>What determines how the factors of production are to be allocated among different production activities in a planned economy<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "equity principle",
      "individual ability to pay",
      "private needs",
      "public needs determined by the government"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 4,
    "examYear": "2015"
  },
  {
    "question": "<p><strong>One of the fundamental differences between capitalist and a socialist state is that while:<\/strong><\/p>",
    "options": [
      "there is equality in distribution of wealth in the socialist state, it is not so in a capitalist economy",
      "in the former, price mechanism guides the allocation of resources, it is the government agency that performs this function in the latter",
      "the former is governed by the principle of the survival of the fittest, the latter is concerned with the welfare of all",
      "taxes are levied in a socialist economy; there is no taxation in capitalist economy"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "examYear": "2015"
  }
]